[Music]
if you want to know what cooking in
Excel layouts for business Central 2025
Wave
1 here is a little sneak peek of what
we're going to
do on um your road Center but you can
also search for it you have a menu
called Excel reports this was in the
past resered to some build-in reports
that um were hard for users to to change
because they were coded in the AL
language but a couple of releases ago we
added new Excel layouts and they are
marked here with a preview the new thing
for wave 1 is that they will be
generally available and I'll just show
you one example and then show you where
you can learn
more so uh let's take a look at a
finance report trial balance over
previous year if I choose this in the
menu and just put in a date filter let
me give take a year of data and run the
report uh and download the report it
will
start working uh its magic on creating
the data set and will'll eventually soon
get a an Excel layout or Excel report
form me let me uh open that in
Excel so the report is ready if I open
from downloads
and here in Excel I need first of all to
enable editing this is just a security
setting in Excel and because this report
is using some power query inside Excel
it's not communicating to the outside
world I need to open for that and then
uh the report will render
one of my favorite things about Excel
layouts let me make it a little bit
smaller
here is that as a user I can completely
change the look and feel for this um if
I don't what I don't like or if there
are things in the Microsoft provided
template that I would like to change a
little bit so maybe I want to remove
this line here let's delete that maybe I
want to have a little less space here
maybe I don't want the the white space
like this because I want the screen
state to show all my data like that and
uh maybe I want to hide a few things
here I'll just hide these tabs here I
don't want to see the data tab I'll hide
that so now my report here is um is the
way I want it maybe I also want to look
move these for the generally available
version we'll likely put these slices to
the right so that they are um the right
place but uh you don't have to think
about that here I can um filter with the
slicers so maybe I want to zoom into my
fixed assets uh categories and uh let's
see if there's any data here I might
also have some of these columns that I
don't want so account type maybe I want
to get rid of that see if I can find
that here in the
pivot table account
type it's down here
under that one so let me just get rid of
this remove field and this is kind of
the report I want and then I can I can
upload this back to business Central
make sure I clear my filters but then
that's kind of the idea with with Excel
so um the the reason for want why this
is a watch cooking video is that you can
already now get a feel for these reports
in our documentation let me show you
how so if I open my browser and put in
this short URL here
BC
Finance
analytics this will take me to a landing
page in the documentation which is about
f Financial
analytics no surprise there if I scroll
down a little bit here and find my
built-in Finance
reports key Finance reports and look at
this landing page you notice that under
the report
overview here if only I can find click
it here we
go that we see a table
of Excel uh or or and also classic
reports so for instance we have a det
detailed trial balance we also have a
trial balance in Excel and we have a
trial balance previous or budget over
balance over budget in Excel so you can
find these uh reports here and if you
choose one of them let's take about uh
this trial balance in Excel you get a
description on what what the report does
you can also get a description of the
worksheets in the report with
screenshots so you can kind of get an
idea of what you can use this for if you
scroll down a bit further there also a
tip here of how you can go to the pivot
table like I showed in the video um you
can use the raw data with co-pilot
there's some descriptions for that other
work uh worksheets use cases how you
could use this report rep for different
for different personas of roles and then
uh there's a link to the report if you
want to try it out so you don't have to
go from business Central you can open it
directly here from the documentation and
some guidance of the example I showed on
how to make the report your own also
with some documentation on how to do
that we even added for some of these
reports links to alternative ways to
analyze this data maybe you want to use
powerbi maybe you want to use the legac
report or maybe you want to use
financial reporting feature and for many
of these reports we also have
contributors here we have Kim teld one
of our MVPs who helped made the article
so go check that out also in the
documentation and uh and try the new
Excel layouts reports right now and also
try them when we release 2025 release
wave one